Guide to the Allen-Angier family papers, 1843-1971 RL.10097
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Allen-Angier family papers
1843-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Allen, George V. (George Venable), 1903-1970
RL.10097
8 Linear Feet 16 boxes
Collection contains correspondence, speeches, clippings, and printed material, chiefly relating to the career of George Venable Allen (1903-1970), diplomat, director of the U.S. Information Agency, and president of the Tobacco Institute. Includes material on the U.S. Foreign Service, the U.S. Information Agency, U.S. foreign relations, India, Iran, the tobacco industry, and the cigarette smoking and health controversy. Also includes family photographs from the Angier house on Trinity Avenue in Durham.
Provenance
The Allen-Angier family papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gifts in 1971-1972, 1993, and 2010.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into two series--Allen Materials and Angier Materials--with two additions that have not been interfiled.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Collection Overview
Collection includes papers kept by Zalene Allen Angier which include correspondence, 1936-1969, largely letters from her brother George Venable Allen (1903-1970), diplomat, official of the Tobacco Institute, and trustee of Duke University.
Allen's letters describe his diplomatic career and personal matters, including foreign relations and social life in Greece, Egypt, and Iran in the 1930s and 1940s; the royal family of Iran; the Potsdam Conference; and customs of Saudi Arabia. Letters of the 1950s mention celebrities Allen met, such as Yehudi Menuhin and Aristotle Onassis; and relations of the U.S. with India and of Russia with Yugoslavia. Letters of Allen's wife Katherine Martin Allen reflect diplomatic social life.
Clippings relate to Allen's career as diplomat and as director of the United States Information Agency, to his family, and to his death.
Miscellaneous papers include invitations; White House dinner menus; press releases; a report, February 9, 1932, on Japanese-Chinese relations; articles by Allen; and other printed materials.
There are photographs of Allen and many acquaintances, including Marshall Tito, Mohammed Reza Pahlavi, Jawaharlal Nehru, Amjad All, Abba Eban, Wellington Koo, Dwight D. Eisenhower, John Foster Dulles, and William Fulbright.
Papers, 1945-1970, kept by George and Katherine Allen include letters from Eisenhower and Dulles about Allen's shift from the State Department to the USIA; a report on the political situation in Iran, January 21, 1948; correspondence on Egyptian-U.S. relations in the 1950s and the Henry A. Byroade scandal, the Cold War, the cigarette smoking and health controversy, and on Allen's speeches.
Enclosed with a letter from Allen of May 10, 1970, is a petition against slavery by the Baptist Church of Augusta, Maine, dated August 17, 1843.
There are files of speeches and related correspondence on Russia, propaganda, the space race, foreign policy, peace, the tobacco industry, India, Iran, UNESCO, and other topics.
There is material on the Dulles and Eisenhower oral history projects and on various honors and awards received by Allen.
Two scrapbooks contain clippings about Allen's career and family photographs. There is also a photocopy of his book-length manuscript reminiscence of experiences as Ambassador to Iran in the 1940s and 1950s; a letter from Josephus Daniels, 1940, commenting on Allen's review of Daniels' book, Tar Heel Editor; and a tape recording of Allen's address, 1967, to the Tobaccoland Kiwanis Club on the United States in the world.
United States -- Foreign relations -- 20th century; Tobacco -- Physiological effect; Diplomatic and consular service; Iran -- History -- 20th century; India -- History -- 20th century; United States. Foreign Service; Tobacco Institute (Washington, D.C.); Allen family; Angier family; United States Information Agency
- Allen Materials, 1843-1971; 5 boxes
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1940-1959 May (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1959 June-Dec. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1970 (Box 1)
  - Subject Files
    - "Basic Themes of U.S. Foreign Policy," Rome, 1965 Nov. 22 (Box 2)
    - Duke Executive Committee (Box 2)
    - California Educators Conference, 1967 Feb. 25 (Box 2)
    - Coe College, Cedar Rapids, Iowa, 1967 Jun. 11 (Box 2)
    - "Diplomacy, Loud or Quiet? Freedom & Union", 1961 Oct. (Box 2)
    - Duke Executive Committee (Box 2)
    - Federal Union Luncheon, 1964 April 16 (Box 2)
    - Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Creel Conference, 1967 May 29 (Box 2)
    - Freedom Assembly at the Overseas Press Club, NYC, speech, 1961 Oct. 7 (Box 2)
    - "Germany revisited," write-up of visit to Germany, 1964 October (Box 2)
    - Honors and Awards (Box 2)
    - How Foreign Policy is Made, 1964 Oct. (Box 2)
    - Hanover College, Indiana, commencement address, 1966 May 29 (Box 2)
    - Harvard-Radcliffe Student Government Association, 1967 Feb. 2 (Box 2)
    - Hood College, Frederick, Md., 1967 Mar. 6 (Box 2)
    - "How U.S. Foreign Poclity is Made" (Box 2)
    - Hunter College, 1967 June 8 (Box 2)
    - Oral History Project on Eisenhower Administration (Box 2)
    - Interview, John Foster Dulles Oral History Project, Princeton University Library, 1965 July 29 (Box 2)
    - Inter-American Defense College, speech, Fort McNair, D.C., 1966 Mar. 10 (Box 3)
    - International Visitors & Sister Cities Conference, mayor's council, 1967 Jan. 28 (Box 3)
    - "Must We Be Red or Dead?" Founder's Day, Duke, 1961 Dec. 11 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - National Secretaries Association, Sheraton Park Hotel, D.C., 1967 Oct. 14 (Box 3)
    - National Tobacco Tax Association, Philadelphia, Pa., summary of address, 1964 Sept. 21 (Box 3)
    - Nehru - Saturday Review article for USIS book, 1965 May 11 (Box 3)
    - "Our Libraries Overseas," Atlantic Monthly, 1961 May (Box 3)
    - North Georgia College, Dahlonega, Ga., 1966 June 5 (Box 3)
    - Pennsylvania State University (Box 3)
    - People to People (Box 3)
    - Pharmaceutical Manufacturers annual meeting, Boca Raton, Fla., 1967 Mar. 31 (Box 3)
    - Princeton speech, 1962 (Box 3)
    - "Some Thoughts on Career Service," State Newsletter, 1964 June (Box 3)
    - Spartanburg, S.C., 1966 Jan. (Box 3)
    - State University College, New Paltz, N.Y., 1966 Oct. 18 (Box 3)
    - "Success in Training," article for Success Unlimited, 1967 July (Box 3)
    - "The Suez Affair," book review for Interplay, 1967 Jun. (Box 3)
    - "To Tell the Truth", 1967 Feb. 2 (Box 3)
    - "Understanding: The Surest Road to Peace," G.E. Defense Quarterly, 1959 July 9 (Box 3)
    - "Meet the Press", 1958 (Box 3)
    - Tobacco Institute, Inc. (Box 3)
    - Walter Johnson High School, Bathesda, Md. (commencement address), 1967 Jun. 20 (Box 3)
    - World Affairs Council of Northern Calif., San Francisco, 1967 Oct. (Box 3)
    - "Whose Ambassador," by Fitzpatrick (Box 3)
    - Review of "The Strategy of Subversion," by Prof. Paul L. Blackstock, Saturday Review, 1964 Oct. (Box 3)
    - "Yugoslavia and the West", 1950 (Box 3)
    - United States Information Agency (USIA), 1957-1963 (Box 4)
  - United States Information Agency (USIA), 1958-1963
    - "USIA: The Big Problem is Belief," NY Herald Tribune, 1963 Aug. 4 (Box 4)
    - USIA speeches, 1958 (Box 4)
    - USIA speeches, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Binder of USIA speeches, 1957-1960 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Writings and Addresses, 1939-1970
    - Writings and addresses, 1939-1958 (Box 5)
    - Writings and addresses, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
    - Writings and addresses, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Writings and addresses, 1962-1965 Sept. (Box 5)
    - Writings and addresses, 1965 Oct. - 1970 (Box 5)
    - "Mission to Iran," Chapters 1-5 (Box 5)
    - "Mission to Iran," Chapters 6-10 (Box 5)
- Angier Materials, 1930s-1970s; 3 boxes
  - Correspondence, 1936-1969
    - Correspondence, 1936-1957 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1969; undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellany, 1932-1970s
    - Miscellany, 1932-1963 (Box 6)
    - Miscellany, 1966-1970s (Box 6)
  - Clippings, 1930s-1970s
    - Clippings: Greece, 1950s (Box 6)
    - Clippings: India, 1950s (Box 6)
    - Clippings: Middle East, 1950s (Box 6)
    - Clippings: Yugoslavia, 1950s (Box 6)
    - Clippings: USIA, 1950s (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1930s-1940s (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1950s (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1960s (Box 7)
    - Clippings: Tobacco Institute, 1960s (Box 7)
    - Clippings: Duke University, 1960s (Box 7)
    - Clippings: Foreign Service Institute, 1960s (Box 7)
    - Clippings: USIA, 1960s (Box 7)
    - Clippings: Presidential Campaign, 1964 (Box 7)
    - Clippings, 1970; undated (Box 7)
  - Printed Materials
    - Printed materials, 1940-1959 (Box 7)
    - Printed materials, 1960-1961 July (Box 7)
    - Printed materials, 1961 July - 1965 (Box 7)
    - Printed materials, 1966-1970 (Box 7)
    - Broadside, 1960 Nov. 14 (Box 7)
  - Photographs and Tape Recordings
    - Photographs: Atoms for Peace (Box 8)
    - Photographs: Belgium (Box 8)
    - Photographs: China (Box 8)
    - Photographs: Family (Box 8)
    - Photographs: Greece (Box 8)
    - Photographs: India (Box 8)
    - Photographs: Iran (Box 8)
    - Photographs: Lebanon (Box 8)
    - Photographs: Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Photographs: Nepal (Box 8)
    - Photographs: Yugoslavia (Box 8)
    - Photographs: Pakistan (Box 8)
    - Tape Recording: "The Position of the U.S. in the World" (Box 8, Audio-reel RL10097-RR-0001, Digital-materials RL10097-SET-0001, Audio-file RL10097-RR-0001.wav)
- Allen-Angier Family Papers addition, 1819-1974; 2 boxes
  - Foreign Service diary (Box 1 of 2)
  - Correspondence, 1906-1974 (Box 1 of 2)
  - Addresses and writings, 1929-1968 (Box 1 of 2)
  - Financial papers, 1819-1907 (Box 1 of 2)
  - Miscellany and photographs (Box 1 of 2)
  - Printed materials (Box 1 of 2)
  - Clippings, 1948-1970 (Box 1 of 2)
  - Scrapbooks and a photograph album (Box 2 of 2)
- Accession (1993-0171), circa 1930s-1960s; 6 boxes
  - Correspondence, 1931-1966; undated (Box 93/171: 1)
  - Miscellany (Box 93/171: 1)
  - Clippings, 1935-1964 (Box 93/171: 2)
  - Photographs (Box 93/171: 3)
  - Family scrapbook (Box 93/171: 4)
  - Scrapbook of clippings and family scrapbook (Box 93/171: 5)
  - Family scrapbooks, clippings, and photographs (Box 93/171: 6)